And you thought we'd never get here.
Get it 여기까지 못 올 줄 알았죠?
Here we are in Jupyter Lab, running our fine tuning for a frontier model.
주피터 연구소에서 개척지 모델을 세밀하게 조정하고 있어요
So we start with a bunch of imports.
수입 부품부터 시작하죠
We also import the test data.
테스트 데이터도 가져오죠
If you remember, this is that nifty piece of code that is able to run through 250 test examples and
기억하신다면 이건 250개의 테스트 예제를 실행할 수 있는 실용적인 코드입니다 아름다운
give us a beautiful chart.
차트를 제공하죠
At the end of it, we load in our environment, we load in hugging face token, which we're not going
마지막에 우리 환경에서 끌어안는 얼굴 토큰을 로드합니다 이번에는 사용하지 않겠지만
to use this time, but like before, why not always like hugging and hugging face?
이전처럼 항상 끌어안고 얼굴을 안는 건 어떨까요?
And we are going to use OpenAI.
오픈AI를 사용할 거예요
So we very much need to run that line there and here.
그래서 저 선을 저기와 여기에 실행해야 해요
And again we're going to do this where we open the training data and the test data from a pickle file
피클 파일에서 훈련 데이터와 테스트 데이터를 열어 이걸 하도록 하겠습니다
so that we don't have to recreate everything from scratch in it comes.
모든 걸 처음부터 다시 만들 필요가 없도록요
All right.
좋아요
So let's talk about what we're going to do now.
이제 뭘 할지 얘기해보죠
So OpenAI recommends that when you're doing training you use somewhere between 50 and 100 example points
오픈AI는 여러분이 훈련할 때 훈련에 사용한 예시를 50-100개 정도 사용하라고
that you use for training.
권장해요
And really the the main intention of fine tuning for a frontier model is about adapting its tone and
개척지 모델의 세밀한 조정은 음색과 스타일을 바꾸는 거예요 오류를
style, and correcting for errors and improving accuracy in some circumstances.
수정하고 어떤 상황에서는 정확도를 높이는 거죠
Um, there's not a massive point in, in putting in enormous numbers of examples, because a model like
중요한 건 아니고 예시를 많이 넣는 것도 큰 의미가 없어요 GPT 4 시리즈 같은 모델은 너무 많은 데이터를 바탕으로
the GPT four series is trained on so much data that what you're really trying to do is just give it
훈련되어서 여러분이 정말 하려는 건 여러분이 원하는 특정 작업의 예시를 충분히
enough examples of something specific you want it to do, so it can learn from that.
제공하는 거예요 그래야 거기서 배울 수 있죠
Um, so yeah, there's um, not not a recommendation to go to a very large number, but I'm at the very
네, 아주 많은 숫자를 추천하지 않는 건 아니지만 적어도 500은
least going to pick 500 here, which is more than they recommend.
뽑을 거예요 권장량보다 많죠
Uh, and I've tested it and it does better than, than smaller numbers.
그리고 제가 실험해 봤는데 작은 수치보다 결과가 좋았어요
Um, and so I'm picking 500 of our examples.
500가지 예시를 들어볼게요
Now our examples are very small.
지금은 아주 작은 사례만 있죠
Our text is very small and I think typically there they are thinking about much bigger training documents.
텍스트는 아주 작아요 일반적으로 훨씬 더 큰 훈련 문서를 생각하고 있죠
So because of that, I don't feel bad about this.
그래서 저는 전혀 미안하지 않아요
And at the moment this is actually fine tuning.
지금은 미세한 조율이에요
Um, is is free for a period of time until I think it's September the 23rd, but later in September.
한동안은 비어요 9월 23일까지는요 9월 말까지는요
But even when it stops being free, the cost you pay is similar to the cost to actually just run inference
하지만 무료가 아니게 되더라도 여러분이 지불하는 비용은 500개에 대한 추론만 수행하는
on 500 of these, which is measured in a few cents again.
비용과 비슷합니다 이것도 역시 몇 센트로 측정되죠
So at this point, I imagine we're talking about about $0.05 to do this, uh, for, for or equivalent
그럼 지금으로서는 0달러 정도 되겠네요 5천 달러요, 그 정도 금액으로요
Um, so it's still small pennies.
여전히 적은 금액이네요
And as I say, it's free at least until late September.
말씀드렸듯이 9월 말까지는 무료예요
So with that, I'm dividing into a training set of 500 from the actual training set that we've got,
500개의 훈련 세트를 만들었어요 실제 훈련 세트인 400,000개와
which is 400,000.
비교해서요
Uh, and I'm going to take 50 as validation.
50달러로 검증 받을게요
I mentioned a moment ago, we don't actually need to do validation because our training set, we're
아까 언급했듯이 검증은 필요 없습니다 훈련 세트에서 한 번만
only going to do one epoch through it.
할 것이기 때문이죠
Um, but I thought it'd be useful to show it to you so that you know how to do this for the future in
하지만 여러분께 보여드리면 유용할 것 같았어요 나중에 여러분 프로젝트에서 어떻게 사용할지
in your projects.
알 수 있게요
Because all of this can be replicated for your projects.
이 모든 게 여러분의 프로젝트에 따라 복제될 수 있거든요
So we run this.
이걸 실행해요
So I mentioned to you that the first step is preparing the Jsonl JSON lines data, converting our training
첫 단계는 Jsonl JSON 라인 데이터를 준비하는 거라고 말씀드렸죠 훈련 데이터를 이 포맷으로
data into this format.
변환하는 거예요
So first of all, I wrote a method that a function that you know well messages for uh, which is taken
먼저 여러분이 잘 아는 메서드 함수를 작성했어요 메시지를 전달하는 함수죠 지난 시간에 했던
exactly from what we did last time.
것과 정확히 일치해요
Uh, it says you estimate prices of items, reply only with the price, no explanation.
물품의 가격을 추정하고 가격으로만 답해야 해요 설명하지 말고요
And then for the user prompt, I take the test prompt from the item.
사용자 프롬프트는 아이템에서 테스트 프롬프트를 가져오고요
Um, and I strip out to the nearest dollar and just replace that with uh, and with with empty.
그리고 1달러가 될 만한 건 다 빼고 빈 지폐로 바꿔요
So it's not it's not directing it to only go to the nearest dollar, The frontier Labs need no such
최저 금액을 제시하는 게 아닙니다 개척지 연구소는 그런 추측이
approximation.
필요 없죠
And I also take out that, um, and that's what goes in the user prompt.
그리고 이것도 빼요 그게 사용자 프롬프트에 가는 거죠
And then I reply with the assistant saying price is and then giving the price.
그럼 전 보조에게 가격을 말하고 가격을 알려줘요
So let's run that.
실행해 보죠
And just in case it's not clear what's going on, let's just give you an example.
무슨 일인지 잘 모르실 수 있으니 예를 들어볼게요
Messages for train zero, which will be the first one that the model sees.
모델이 처음 보는 0번 열차에 보내는 메시지예요
And this is what you get roll system.
Get 롤 시스템이에요
And that's the system prompt.
시스템 프롬프트죠
Check you're happy with that and then roll user.
만족스러운지 확인하고 사용자를 롤해요
And this is the user prompt.
이게 사용자 프롬프트예요
Uh it's as if we have asked this question how much does this cost question mark.
우리가 이 질문을 한 것 같네요 물음표는 얼마일까요?
And then this spiel about a Delphi or Delphi, Delphi, uh, fuel pump module.
델포이 어쩌고 하는 장황한 얘기도 들었어요 연료 펌프 모듈요
Um, and then the This is the assistant's response.
그리고 이건 비서의 대답이에요
The price is $226.
가격은 226달러예요
I would never have I well, I remember, I didn't guess that it was anything like that.
그런 건 상상도 못 했어요 그런 건 상상도 못 했죠
Uh, so there you go.
자, 보세요
You learn something every day.
매일 새로운 걸 배우네요
Anyway, this is the format of the messages, which is something that should be very, very familiar
어쨌든 이게 메시지 형식입니다 이 단계에선 아주 익숙할
to you at this stage.
거예요
And you can see how this is a perfectly crafted test, sorry, training data point that we will be providing
이게 어떻게 완벽하게 만들어진 테스트, 아니 훈련 데이터 포인트인지 알 수 있습니다 우리가 모델에
to the model.
제공할 것이죠
Okay, so then here is a function make JSON L that is going to do just what you would think it will
좋아요, 여기 JSON L을 만드는 함수가 있어요 여러분이 예상하는 대로 항목을 여러
take in a bunch of items.
개 받아들이죠
It will iterate through those items.
그런 항목을 반복할 거예요
It will create this text, this, this, uh, object for each one.
각각의 객체를 위해 텍스트를 생성하죠
And then it will use Json.dumps dump string to convert that into a simple string.
그런 다음 Json을 사용하죠 덤프 스트링을 덤프 스트링으로 전환해 단순한 문자열로 변환하죠
And then look, it just simply adds that to this one string with a carriage return at the end of it.
보세요, 문자열 하나에 추가하고 끝에 캐리지 리턴을 하죠
And then I return that back and I strip out that last carriage return.
그리고 다시 리턴합니다 마지막 캐리지 리턴을 제거하고요
So let's see this in action.
어떻게 작동하는지 보죠
So let's say let's run it first.
먼저 실행해 보죠
Don't make my usual blunder.
나처럼 실수하지 마요
There we go.
됐어요
And now say make JSON.
이제 만들기를 해요 JSON
L uh, and let's pass in uh, some of our training data.
훈련 데이터를 제출하도록 하죠
Let's just pass in the first three of that so we don't crowd everything out.
앞의 세 곡만 통과시키죠 그래야 사람들이 안 몰려요
So here we get back a string, of course.
get get get 문자열이죠
And it's a string which has, uh.
그리고 문자열도 있어요
It might be easier if we print it.
인쇄하는 게 더 쉬울 것 같아요
Let's print it so that we get empty lines clearly showing through.
get을 해서 빈 선이 잘 보이게 만들어 줄게요
Okay, so it's a string and you can see one, two, three lines in the string.
문자열입니다 문자열에 1, 2, 3개의 줄이 있죠
Um, it's sort of wrapping around.
좀 휘감기고 있어요
And you can see that each row has in it, um, the, the full messages exchanged for the represents
각 행에 있는 메시지를 보면 훈련 데이터 포인트를 나타내요
Okay.
네
So far so good.
지금까진 좋아요
Now we have this function just building on that.
이제 그 위에 구축된 함수가 있어요
Right?
그렇죠?
Jsonl take items and takes a file name.
Jsonl은 항목을 취하고 파일 이름을 취해요
And this is super simple stuff.
아주 간단해요
Opens that file name and calls the function above and writes it out.
파일 이름을 열고 위의 함수를 호출해 써요
So I don't think I need to to give you a demo of that one.
그에 대한 데모는 드릴 필요가 없을 것 같네요
I do need to execute it, but we can actually run it.
실행해야 하지만 실제로 실행할 수 있어요
So we're going to take our training data set, which you remember the fine tuned train which is 500
이제 훈련 데이터 집합을 볼게요. 잘 조율된 트레인 기억하시죠? 500개의 아이템이 있어요.
items.
확인해 보죠
There it is, 500 items from the training data set overall, which is 400,000.
됐어요, 훈련 데이터 세트 전체에서 500개, 400,000개예요
We're not going to we're not going to write all of them to a file and upload them to GPT four.
전부 파일에 작성해 GPT 4에 업로드 하진 않아요
Uh, so, um, we we write that out to a file called Fine Tune train dot JSON.
파인 튠 트레인 닷 JSON 파일에 그걸 적어요
L let's run that and then we'll take the validation set and do exactly the same run that.
그걸 실행하고 유효성 검증 세트를 가져다가 정확히 같은 걸 실행하죠
So we've written those two files and you can see they just wrote a couple of seconds ago.
저 두 파일을 작성했는데 몇 초 전에 작성된 걸 보실 수 있죠
So if I open this up, I can open it.
이걸 열면 열 수 있어요
There is actually a fancy JSON lines editor in, uh, in JupyterLab, but we're just going to go over
JupyterLab에도 JSON 라인 편집기가 있어요 일반 편집기로
a normal editor.
넘어가 보죠
And here you can see, just as you'd expect, we're expecting 500 rows.
여러분이 기대하는 대로 500개의 행이 있네요
Here we go, all the way down to the end, 500 rows it is.
자, 끝까지 갑니다 500줄이네요
And they all have exactly the structure that you would hope.
모두 우리가 바라는 구조로 이루어져 있어요
Um, and you can see this actually isn't well-formed JSON because, uh, each line is a well-formed
잘 구성된 JSON이 아닌 걸 알 수 있어요 각 행은 잘 구성된 JSON 문서거든요
I know I'm belaboring that point, but it is it is important you wouldn't be able to read this in and
제가 장황하게 말하고 있지만 이걸 읽을 수 없고 JSON 문서로 파싱할
parse it as a JSON document, because it's a not well-formed JSON.
수 없는 게 중요해요 구성이 잘 된 JSON이 아니니까요
It's separate lines.
선이 분리돼 있어요
Um, and the validation file open with editor is just, I think 50.
에디터로 여는 검증 파일이 50개 정도 될 거예요
We said 50 lines much the same way.
50줄은 거의 비슷하게 말했어요
Uh, I can I'll just show you what it looks like in the JSON lines.
JSON 라인에서 어떻게 보이는지 보여드릴게요
Editor.
편집자요
It's a fancy editor that looks like this.
이렇게 생긴 멋진 편집기예요
And you can open up each one and it's like a JSON object.
각각을 열 수 있어요 JSON 개체 같죠
Uh.
네
Look at that.
보세요
That's how I should have started.
그렇게 시작을 했어야죠
Probably.
아마도요
It gives you a very good sense of what's going on.
어떤 상황인지 잘 알 수 있죠
Uh, it's a very intuitive sense of the way the reason why messages are packaged.
메시지가 왜 포장되는지에 대한 직관적인 감각을 발휘하죠
The way they're packaged.
포장된 방식요
All right, so that are those are the files.
좋아요, 그게 파일이에요
Uh, that's the last step of this.
그게 마지막 단계예요
This part.
이 부분요
Um, it will be time for us to upload these files to OpenAI.
오픈AI에 업로드 할 때가 된 것 같아요
And to do that, we call OpenAI dot files dot create.
OpenAI.Files.Create라고 이름 붙였어요
And we pass in the file and we tell it the purpose is fine tune.
파일을 전달하고 목적이 미세하다고 말하죠
Uh, and just one tiny thing to watch out for.
한 가지 주의할 게 있어요
When you pass in this file, you have to pass it in.
이 파일을 전달할 때 반드시 전달해야 해요
You have to open it as a binary file, because it's just going to be the binary bytes in that file that
이진법 파일로 열어야 합니다. 왜냐하면 그 파일은 바이너리 바이트로 되어 있어서 OpenAI로 스트리밍
will get streamed up to OpenAI.
될 것이니까요.
So you don't want this to be an R, you want it to be an RB.
R이 아니라 RB로 해야 해요
Uh, so just just a small nuance to watch out for.
아주 작은 뉘앙스만 조심하면 돼요
We're just sending the entire contents of the file as is to OpenAI.
파일의 모든 내용을 OpenAI로 보내고 있어요
So we execute that line takes a second.
그 라인을 실행하는 데 1초가 걸리죠
If I just inspect what came back, I get back a file object.
무엇이 돌아왔는지 검사하면 파일 객체를 가져오죠.
It's got a certain number of bytes.
특정 바이트의 개수가 있고요
Object is file, purpose is fine tuned, status is processed.
객체는 파일이고 목적은 잘 조정되었고 상태는 처리되었어요
So already OpenAI is taking that file and has processed it.
OpenAI는 이미 파일을 가져와서 처리하고 있어요
And we will do the same thing for the validation.
검증도 똑같이 할 거예요
We'll run it and there we go.
실행하면 다 됐어요
And once again it is processed.
다시 한 번 처리하죠
So at this point we have created two JSON files.
이 시점에서 우린 두 개의 JSON 파일을 만들었죠
One for our fine tuned training set, one for our fine tuned validation set.
하나는 훈련용이고 하나는 검증용이죠
We've written them out to our file system.
우리 파일 시스템에 적어뒀어요
And then we have uploaded them to OpenAI, where they are now sitting as file objects in OpenAI.
그리고 OpenAI에 업로드했습니다 OpenAI에서 파일 객체로 자리 잡고 있죠
In the next session, we will actually do some fine tuning.
다음 시간에는 미세한 조정을 할 거예요
See you there.
거기서 봐요